All right, so you can have a core area of dealing or trade in, yeah, so buys and sellers are getting matched, hence why price isn't going anywhere, so it's buy liquidity, sell liquidity, and then momentarily it can be just a small area of weakness, yeah, that's one condition, a small area of weakness times by or coupled with a volume shot, so in this instance, market order buy, so that's the second condition, right? And that's enough to trigger that price response to trigger the protective mechanism where the dealer,
takes on the volume and filters it out into the very own book in small pieces.
So it's 100 volume shot, split into small pieces, wherever this cell liquidity, match it off with that,
rather than them taking on the short position of 100 themselves.
So I'm going to see all the dealers respond.
They also avoid taking on short positions.
If there is cell limit sitting in the book, they can't provide it out to the market
because if they provide sell liquidity at this price,
dealer ones already moving higher.
There's a price breakdown, this price discrepancy, so they all have to control the supply of liquidity, effectively, which results in an environment where there is little sell liquidity in the market.
Right.
Now, the point I'm really making is, just because this distortion is on the way, price is drawing away, popping out buy volumes trying to find sell liquidity, this doesn't necessarily mean that this 100 shot volume reflects the total market sentiment.
doesn't really mean that everybody in this market is bullish.
It was a volume shot that came out at the right time
that set off a price response within the market.
The protective mechanism then affects or creates this environment
of lack of sell liquidity and subsequently price pops out.
That condition can exist perfectly fine and simultaneous to.
There's still being a whole bunch of buy liquidity down here.
Yeah, down at the arm.
Do you follow what I'm trying to say?
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
The price can move away from it.
here even though there's still large large unfulfilled orders or a single order down here in the tens of hundreds or you know thousands of millions which is billions so effectively which mean this means basically basically means that once the volume shot dries off it doesn't have to be a huge amount of volume in the first place but once the volume shot dries off it on the way up left behind thinness weakness a thinly traded area a low volume traded area a lack of bi liquidity is in there and
And we know the condition that exists at the exhaustion point, which is weakness, right?
There's less liquidity on the buy side because of the way price traveled up.
These buyers did not chase price higher.
It traded thinly on the way up.
The willingness for buy liquidity to turn up at these higher and higher prices is almost non-existent,
especially considering the amount of volatility on the way up.
Right?
So you have an area of weakness, lack of liquidity is illiquid, aka a vacuum.
The real bi-liquity remains back down to the origin, the core.
And once the volumes dried off, again, like I said,
you have one side of the market, which is less liquid,
and the other side of the market,
it doesn't even have to be that strong,
but typically it'll hit a stronger area of opposing liquidity.
So sell liquidity, it likely will have hit an area with a cell liquidity.
You follow me?
So now what's required to push price down?
We already know those weak bids.
We already know these thicker offers, right?
yeah yeah
what's required
to put price back down
just a scude book
nope
because liquidity
doesn't move the market
what requires
oh
market order sells
yeah
any any
market order sell
that comes through
is very very likely
to push price down
yeah yeah
yeah
you have to think about
this way as well
so there's a whole
in this hypothetical example
there's a billion
willing to transact here
yeah
there's a billion
by liquidity
but wants sellers to hit it
why
that exists that's perfectly separate to this 100 volume shot right because that's liquidity
this is market order yeah the 100 market order comes at the right time there's a bit of cell
weakness uh it triggers the price response price runs out trying to find sell liquidity and like we know
the sell equity is disappearing um at the exhaustion point it's created this whole area that really
shouldn't have existed if the total amount of sell liquidity was being provided to that one volume
shop. But like I said, this is happening internally with one dealer. The necessary sell liquidity at this
price level can be a completely different dealer. And because they deal internally, they internalize
all the information. It's basically impossible for this volume to access the liquidity at this
deal of the dealer. Yeah. He's trading with it. But the point I'm really making here is the real
core here liquidity remains down here. This is a distortion. It's a price. It's an inefficiency,
basically, which shouldn't really exist if it wasn't for the behaviors of these dealers. And then
it's creating this condition where it's quite easy to push price down. It's actually the more
natural thing for price to do is for it to draw down. The willingness to buy up there, the further
price travels, the thinner is getting, this volume shot is getting filled, filled, filled, filled,
the amount of volume that's unfulfilled is obviously getting weaker and weaker.
So the further that price run travels,
the less willingness there is to buy at these prices.
Yeah.
Okay.
And the real core area remains out there.
Now, obviously,
there is environments where buyers can behave in a way
where they're willing to accept higher and higher prices.
So this billion by liquidity might turn up there,
but as you'll come to know,
this is only under event-driven environments or states
so there may be something that just happened
it might be a news event it might be a political event
geopolitical event it just doesn't matter
it could be any number of variables
that affects the sentiment of traders
the attitude of traders
so for example
if we're looking at USDJPI
if there's a whole area
there's a billion dollars worth of buy liquidity
down at this area
suddenly something happens
this volume shock
causes price to move out
we know this billion bi-liquity
is separate
because it's the limit orders
but within that time
imagine new information came out
that threatened, I don't know
the Japanese economy
or so for example
North Korea
has launched a fucking missile
to Japan
is very very likely
within that environment
nobody wants to be
long JPI
right
they want to
quickly cut
or limit any exposure
in the Japanese yen
ideally for
potentially a safer currency
the US dollar
so within that environment
there's going to be
a whole heap
or a high level of urgency
to buy the US dollar
against the Japanese yen
yeah
instantaneously almost
so it's very likely
within this kind of event
driven state which is kind of triggering a sentiment-based response from traders where liquidity
may very likely accept higher prices regardless of where prices go in yeah they follow me so this is
what I would call a macro event or an event basically where it sets off certain price we're basically
the willingness to transact at higher and higher prices on one side of the market it is present but outside of that
more natural conditions, where there is no event, we know in FX that there's two-sided
liquidity. So in other words, to sell liquidity here could be from a on Japanese yet, USJPY,
someone's selling the US dollar, buying the Japaneseian there, that could be Apple,
trying to buy Japanese fucking chips for their phones, yeah? Down here, it could be American investors
who borrow from the Japanese government and buy the US dollar back,
because they earn an interest rate differential from that.
So if I borrow from the Japanese government or the Japanese banks sell you,
and Japanese banks give me $1,000 for 0.2% interest.
Yeah.
I then go buy US dollar and just for owning the US dollar,
I'm earning 1%.
You're earning 0.8% profit interest free of charge.
Okay.
Do you get it?
So there might be some speculative traders trying to buy the U.S. dollar, buy short and the yen.
But the point to making is in more natural conditions, you have two side of liquidity, sellers turn up, buyers turn up, price runs out, the buyers maintain their desired price levels, they're passive, they wait for their price levels to get hit, and the sellers kind of maintain their price levels as well.
there is no aggressive or hardly any aggressive market orders pushing pushing pushing
and buy liquidity chasing chasing at higher and higher prices
okay so um you know when you said um event driven um events uh event driven states um you know
where you've put your your green line at the top how you said that was limits can they
there not be market orders as well the market orders will continue to comment any
way.
Okay.
Market orders will continue to come in anyway, but the larger transactions, so those who trade large
amounts of volume, they don't really like market orders because the level of slippage is
almost unlimited.
Oh yeah.
I can imagine in an event as well.
Yeah.
So to limit volatility, they transact with limit orders.
Okay.
Because a limit order is a price only.
It's a price sensitive order.
You can't get slipped on it, can you?
Yeah, you can get positive slippage
So if I have a buy limit order here
And price triggers my buy limit order
Before the limit orders reach the liquidity provider
Price has gone down here
The order will get filled down here
Okay, yeah
That's better for a buy, yeah?
Because you get to buy at a lower price
Yeah
Now that HSPC evolve algorithm
We looked at the liquidity seeking algorithm
That
You know when it's placing orders in the book
the whole purpose of that liquidity seeking algorithm
is to limit exposure
is to limit transaction costs for their clients
so they offer this algorithm that they've built
for their clients who want to trade in larger amounts
but those clients are likely going to be price sensitive
or cost sensitive
they don't really want to enter the market
at super extreme costs
so HSPC provide this algorithmic solution
for finding liquidity for their orders
yeah okay now you know
in this instance
this kind of
calling the liquidity seeking algorithm
a liquidity seeking algorithm
when they use a limit order is a misnomer
it's technically inaccurate
right because
only a market order finds liquidity
a limit order does not find liquidity
a limit order is liquidity
you get it
so it is a bit of a misnomer
but if we look at that
HSBC evolving again it says places limit orders only it's never a market order
so the point I'm really making is when when large transactions are being placed into the market
they're not done through maybe fucking 10 years ago but as it is today
it's predominantly traded through limit orders in FX
the large transactions as well it gives them the most control over the price that's traded
and also it allows them to split the orders into smaller pieces and just place them in the
book. Okay.
And the whole point around the liquidity seeking algorithm is to limit costs, limit information
leakage, so price doesn't start to move away from their desired area of trading before the orders
are filled. You have to think about it this way. H.SBC has clients, yeah. They obviously
offer liquidity services. They offer prime brokerage. They offer in-house liquidity, so internal
liquidity that they've developed over years. And as a client of HSBC, they have, they have
have a single-dealer platform that they've developed
that you can connect to you directly.
Okay.
They want you to connect through their single-dea platform
because you're trading directly with them then.
Yeah.
You're not sourcing prices from three over-liquity providers.
At least HSBC know who their client is.
They're trading directly on their prices,
and HSPC will kind of, in exchange,
provide them as much client services as possible.
They want to keep them on as a client, basically.
Now, in service of maintenance,
and you know client relationships they over time have built these these other options for
the single-deal platforms the algorithmic execution to lower the cost for their clients it gives them
more control over how large transactions are done you get you get to control the price it cancels
that you get to control the time it starts you get to control everything we don't have those options
yeah yeah um it also offers options where you know so HSBC can trade it in the real market for you
that they're connected to so on EBS or they can just deal it off in-house you get to
control that as well and it basically provides a whole heap of options to their client
which may not then need to go out and source prices from other other banks okay all right
all the banks already done this any any bank or any dealer that provides a single leader platform
now also has an algorithmic suite of up of execution options that their clients can
that their clients can use so it's like an industry
standard. The way large transactions are done is typically through algorithmic execution. And the way
these algorithms work, again, is an industry standard. The same, think about it, one bank offers this
new solution. The other banks know about it. They hire the same type of quant type geeks. They continue
to build the same algorithms until it becomes a very competitive space. And all the banks are
very similar algorithms. Right. So yeah, it's more a,
a standard
splitting large orders into small pieces
hiding the order information
if you were trying to get filled for a billion
you don't want everybody to know that
you want to only reveal maybe
tip of the iceberg 1%
2% of that volume
there's other even more
like tailored solutions
which can measure the amount of volume
being traded that minute
so for example
imagine every single minute
there's 500 million being traded
and that's where you can measure
on one or two dealers.
So on this one dealer,
this algorithm measures
to 500 million is being traded every minute.
Then it's quite reasonable
for you to try and transact 200 million a minute now.
The algorithm might be willing to transact
or it's quite reasonable
for the algorithm to place 200 million,
20 million orders quite frequently
as long as the volume stays that high.
So it can be quite a dynamic process
of filtering volume out in and out of the market.
If the volume's low
and it's only 50 million,
pound 50 million being traded a minute then the volume is ridiculous to expect the you know the algorithm
will not be traded in 200 million per minute yeah you get it so it's uh what do you call it
pro rotted depending on the amount of volume the the volume that the algorithms trading into the
market can change as well but my final point here is um a large amount of large transactions
will be done through limit orders okay so this volume
shot it doesn't even have to be for uh so yeah this volume shot it doesn't have to be from a
speculative trader it might literally be someone who's connected to the single legal platform at a bank
they don't need the alga option they're just a small corporation a relatively small corporation
let's say they got a balance sheet of 50 million um and they need to limit some exposure in the japanese
you know they they wish they had um let's say they had an investment in japan they again they wanted to buy
some form of, I don't know, TVs or bikes or whatever, but they didn't use all the money,
so they need to get out of the rest of their currency back into the US dollar.
They short it immediately, 100 million the buy it back.
That's quite reasonable.
The source of liquidity, the source of volume and FX is so wide and that, it's such a big
variety, that it's almost impossible to pinpoint why prices moving in a specific direction.
This volume could be non-speculative.
This corporation that's buying the US dollar back, it doesn't really give too.
focus about where price is going but the volume comes in at the right time where there's
sufficient weakness on the sell liquidity and the liquidity provider responds in a way where they don't
want to take on that risk yeah you get it and the behavior of the dealer within that specific
environment within a kind of generic trend or a general trend of internalizing volume results in
this where they start to deal it off in house it triggers the response to everybody else
sell liquidity broadly disappears um you have to think about
this as well yeah when you have the dealer pulling prices higher all the other dealers respondent
yeah there's also going to be hFT firms which are going to try and aggressively capture the ask
price of the cheaper price imagine one dealer moved prices so this dealer moved from one to two
and then dealer number two also moved to one to two but zero point zero zero zero zero zero zero zero one
seconds later yeah they can they're that faster they can't they that will
exploit it yeah so this firms out they're also trying to buy here so based based on this guy's
slowness this based on this guy's slow speed and then when this guy buys the liquidity provider just
sold him by sold to him by accident now the liquidity provider has to get out of that position as well so
he buys it back so you can have a dynamic where these hFT firms are aggressively causing extra
buying to happen but it's not necessarily always the case because the liquidity
provider they have the option for last look what that means is if they did make a mistake by
selling the HFT they can reverse that transaction they can say no we don't want to that was a
price discrepancy that was an error that's one thing that these dealers have is the the last
lock option which basically means if you buy with the bank and they have like a 200 millisecond
period to review that transaction if in that 200 millisecond period it comes back that that
there was a pricing error
that they are over their risk limit
if it came back that the
HFT firm is trying to just exploit their
price and efficiency
they do have the right
to cancel that trade reverse that trade
so you know when they do that
is there an amount of how many times they can do it
or do you think that it's just
whenever so this is the problem with OTC
it's largely unregulated yeah
banks there was a
recent lawsuit against them from some of their clients that the banks will use in last look
too much or unfairly because the bank says they will have to use this last look because there
is so many price providers and the price moves so much they can be price breakdowns and if they
you know if there's some kind of aggressive predatory type participant exploit in that it's not
fear for the banks so for them to continue providing price low spreads to everybody if they're
going to provide Ulo spreads, Melo spreads,
Milos spreads, everybody,
they have to have the LestLock option there.
So that's what the banks say.
But the banks were using LastLock
outside of the scope of what they said it's for.
And they were actually,
so what they would do is an order would come in from a client.
Obviously, they get to look at it for 200 milliseconds.
But within that 200 milliseconds,
they'd be able to buy it multiple times.
Yeah.
Cause pricing to go higher and then re-quote it
back to their client at a higher price.
Basically, give them a higher price.
so they were doing that somewhat it's technically illegal but it's hard to prove because they
unregulated they did end up admitting it they did end up paying out that's why the last
use of last lock is frowned upon somewhat like I said that's banks that offered that reserve
this right yeah remember how we said there's non-bank market makers yeah who came into the
market when they start to access eBS because they operate on such a fast basis it's so
technologically advanced at that time at least
they came out with this new standard
not only were they offering really really tight spreads
0.1 pips spreads but they were also offering
no last look so you can just imagine
how they were kind of pricing out or competing
against the banks so much
they were basically such a
there were a better option for everybody at that point
had no last look they were openly saying they don't need last look
and simultaneously they were offering
from super tight spruits.
So the banks kind of had to catch up.
They can't really use Last Lock in a super aggressive way anymore.
Okay.
Now, the way they do use it,
look, so there's different ways to do that you can trade with banks here.
On a disclosed basis, so when you trade in directly on a single-lead platform,
the bank knows who you are.
They know if you're a corporate client.
They know if you're a hedge fund.
It's on a disclosed basis.
The identities are revealed before the trade.
All right.
or you can trade on an anonymous basis
on a multi-dealer platform
so here you have a table
similar to an exchange
liquidity providers
they place liquidity in this exchange
or ECN
aka multi-deal platform
is basically all the same thing
and you can connect to it as well
but your identity is hidden
at least before the trade
so here's Zane
he goes long gone
LP1's prices
before LP1 could
fill you he did not know
who you are only the trade is disclosed
after it's happened
so in this event after the trade
is closed or after
no after it's filled
so after Zane has gone long
LP1 has accepted it then
post trade post trade like a few milliseconds after
the identities are revealed
so that's semi-anonymous
now within this kind of dynamic
the LPs have to be
super careful. So imagine
like you are a high HFT firm.
Right. And if
every single time
when it's semi-anonymous by the way
they also reserve the right to last look
because think about it this way. If there was
no last look, HFT firm
Zane aggressively
buys at this LP
causes prices to move against him.
All the other LP start
withdrawing liquidity. So this LP's left
with the short position that he can't do anything with.
It's called toxic flow.
now if that happened
the LP could not
last look and cancel that transaction
or at least
if the LP could not identify
that it's saying
then the LP is no
there's no reason for him to provide tight spreads
on this venue he will start
providing wider spreads and go to 1.5 pips
are you following me
yeah he's getting done over basically and he can't identify
who's doing him over
they will just start to price you out
by giving you wider spreads
so typically these venues
that run these multi-dealer platforms
these liquidity providers reserve
the right to have post-trade
you know the post-trade identities are revealed
and they reserve the right to last lock
but it's all overseen by the multi-dealer platform operator
the LP can't just like last lock any and everything
think about it this way as well you have
LP posting, LP2
posting on this multi-dealer platform
then you have LP2 posting on the next
multi-dealer platform
and then you have LP2 posting on another
on each of these platforms
this dealer is
this dealer is posting 5 million each
5 million there 5 million there 5 million there
a smart HFT firm could buy 5, buy 5,
buy 5 simultaneously
off the same liquidity provider
effectively making the liquidity provider
they go short 15 million at the most expensive sell price doing them over that way right and again
if the LP could not identify who's doing this aggressively predatorially he will again stop pricing
that tightly so all of these multi-dealer platforms to an extent have to maintain some kind of
they have to kind of let these dealers have less luck if they did it your spreads wider you do have
like very like properly anonymous
spend use something like
LMAX
where there is absolutely
no last look LMAX operates
this exchange type
limit order book so it's
a central limit order book
so there's one order book
the dealers post liquidity on there
you can post liquidity on their limit orders
etc etc yeah yeah
but LMAX they don't give
the liquidity providers the right to have last look
So what the liquidity providers do is the price their bid and asks a bit wider.
If you look at the average spreads for GVPUST on LMAX, it's between 0.8 pips to 1.1 pips.
Yeah, you're right.
Whereas if you look at the spread for GbPUSD on Saxo banks, on Saxo banks, forget Saxo Bank, yeah.
If you looked at Elmax, sorry, the GVPUSD feed for current.
X, which is a third-party aggregator of a multi-dealer platform,
their spread's literally going to be between 0.2 to 0.4 pips.
You follow me.
So the point I'm really making here is if the bank, the liquidity provider, can see your identity.
They can see you.
There's no visor in the middle.
They can see your Zane.
It's very likely me, any retail trader you know, they'll class yourself uninformed.
if we're classed as uninformed
they'll continue to give us
the tightest of spreads possible
because they know they can trade against you
over time you'll lose money
I'll lose money that's what they will class of retail
trade rights
if you are a client and
your large hedge fund
is very unlikely
very very unlikely
they'll be taken the opposite side of your trade
because they'll class you as informed
but that only really works
if it's a disclosed basis
now a better solution to that
trading on a semi if you're a hedge fund
trading on a semi-anonymous basis
so trading through a multi-dealer platform
where your identity is only disclosed post the trade
yeah that way the hedge fund
as long as he's not doing like predatory
aggressive type shit by basically doing the LPs over
using speed advantages are the hedge funds that fast
or can they be that fast
so XTX markets which is a non-bank market maker
is basically cast as a hedge fund
okay you have hedge funds with
different purposes as well, yeah? It's a, it's a large, large term that a lot of things fall
under. You can have macro hedge funds, which trade in line with their macro view of the UK economy
or whatever currency that they look at, and they'll just be placing large, large amounts of,
of cash, basically, into these assets. It might be, might be currencies, it might be equities,
typically it's equities, they're just looking for returns. You then have, hey, frequency trading
hedge funds which typically just operate as liquidity providers and market makers around the
best bid best offer prices so the top of work they're the ones that behave in the ways that we've
discussed yeah but they're a hedge fund as well so the hedge fund term it falls under there's a lot
of like types of firms that fall under it as long as the hedge fund isn't aggressively pricing or
aggressively it basically if it's not classed as toxic flow for the liquidity provider they'll
continue to get decent execution and before the trade's executed the liquidity provider will never
know who they're trading with so they can't kind of price them out as long as the flow again
doesn't end up being toxic yeah all right if it is does it end up being toxic and the hFT firm
will start to receive wider spreads that the liquidity provider they'll continue to give good prices
to him good prices to him but this guy will go on the let's say the toxic flow list he'll get
wider spreads. In order for the liquidity
provider to do that, there has to be some
kind of capacity within the
platform they're putting liquidity on for
them to segment clients,
for them to categorize clients.
If they're toxic, you get wider
spreads. If you're benign,
you get the best of spreads.
If you're informed,
you will probably
have to source prices from multiple
liquidity providers. You can't just trade directly with one
liquidity provider because then he'll just
continue to avoid taking on risk
against you.
You follow me.
So larger byside firms,
this is how
they basically work, yeah.
You have your firm, the hedge fund.
You have their prime broker.
If it's a very large hedge fund,
there'll be a prime broker through a bank.
The prime broker then will
source prices that
the hedge fund selects from
as just say,
bank one, bank two, because they've done
their analysis, the transactional cost
analysis, which basically checks
that when the hedge fund trades with
this bank, he doesn't give them
wide prices. He gives them good prices
over time. So they have to
do this kind of analysis.
But what they're doing here is they're building their private
equity pool. Do you get it?
They're getting prices from him,
him, him, and him.
This one might be a third party
aggregate in firms, so like an ECN, a
current X. It might be from
hotspot. So what they have is a
curation of bank liquidity providers.
third-party institutions
and they might even also have
a non-bank market maker as well
and they're sourced in the best prices from them
because they've selected each of these banks
and each of these venues.
This is typically how
and what's essentially,
what happens is it gets the prices
from all these individual venues or banks.
The prime broker is hooked up to them.
It takes these prices, aggregates it up
through the pricing engine
and then the hedge fund is receiving a best bid best offer.
Can't that change
like any
like millisecond
Say again
Can't the best bid and best offer
Like change like
So many times
So if you want to know
How they actually hooked up
You have these large data centers
It's called Equinex
They
They provide purpose-built solutions
Yeah
To make a really long story short
You have these computers there
That the banks
That the banks are putting prices into
So that's Deutsche Bank's computer
this is
HSBC's computer
this is JP Morgan's
computer do you get it
and they update and their prices
millions of times a second
okay okay okay if the bank
doesn't update its prices
millions of times a second
then whoever's the slowest
that gets arbitraged against
think about these guys update
their prices from one to two
one to two
if this guy's a bit slower
then you buy here and sell to him immediately
you catch your money
so they're
forced. If you want to be
liquidity provided today, you have to have the necessary infrastructure
at the relevant data centers.
And if you're not updating your prices as quick as possible,
you will get exploited. So these guys are updating their prices
a million times a second. Now, that's at the data center,
what effectively happens is the hedge fund will rent a rack.
So they will take their own circle, basically. Within the circle,
they'll have they'll be running a software
which is the pricing engine
it takes all the
there's a physical connection
so there's a hard fiber optic wire
that's the same distance
25 meters each
that connects with the rack
of the hedge fund
and within that rack that computer
they're running a software
which is aggregating all the volume
from all the prices from these guys
and creating the best bit best offer
it's also going to handle the order management as well.
So when a buy limit order is placed,
it makes sure it's placed at the right price, et cetera, et cetera.
Now, the hedge fund can run some algorithms directly on that server themselves
so that try to exploit these price and efficiencies,
or they can connect to this through the internet through a fixed API,
which is basically a type of connection.
And then they'll have a server that they can connect to remotely
from their own offices.
But as you can imagine,
then they have to cross the internet.
It takes a bit of a while longer.
But the point of making is this necessary infrastructure,
this aggregation engine,
this pricing engine,
this order management system,
these are all purpose-built solutions
from technology companies
just to make sure that these guys
get the right prices at the right time.
There is no room for error
when you're talking about
huge, huge amounts of volume.
to be traded, you're going to have
the necessary infrastructure. Just the same
way, if you have Virgin Media
Internet, the infrastructure is BT.
I'm sure the lines outside
of our houses, they're BT
or in the ground.
You get it. Virgin
media is just riding on that infrastructure.
You have, I think
BT before, I think in like the 1990s
was a, there were a very,
very large. You know what?
You know why cable's called cable, right?
There was a huge fibrocter cable that was laid out from the English channel, I don't know, all the way over the world, yeah?
That's why GBUSD is called cable.
I think it would have been a company like BT or something that put that cable down or that would have run the infrastructure around it, you get it.
Okay.
So all of these, like to make sure that price is updated all the time, if you were a client that wanted to connect this way directly with the back.
banks prices, you'd have to source, not only a prime broker, you'd have to go to a technology
company that gives you the infrastructure, you'd have to have your own in-house coders that
you employ on a, that they give you your employees to oversee these systems.
So yeah, like, it is quite advanced in terms of the structure, but going back to the point,
limit orders.
The way large transactions are done is kind of a standardized method.
those orders are placed into the book
so the point I'm really making is
at the right time
they can be the right bit of cell weakness
and the right amount of volume
from a completely unexpecting
from a completely unspeculative client
that sets off that price response
but within normal market conditions
whoever has the real liquidity down here
the real market liquidity
just trading within that range isn't it
it can stay down here unfulfilled
So you have 100 million by limit order or by limit orders,
they can maintain their price level here.
We know this price movement out is weak.
Once it dries off or it hits an area of sell liquidity or both,
that weakness of the bids is open for cell volume to push price down.
And typically price will come back here again.
It'll grab the buy liquidity, trade here for a minute,
then a new volume shot is able to push price up.
Because on the way down, it kind of does the same thing.
It traded in low volume.
if there was no bi-liquidity here
or hardly any bi-liquity here
how can loads of selling happen here
no real selling happens there
so you always have these areas of low volume
and high areas of volume that gets to transact
because there's not some liquidity there
and liquidity providers
kind of creating these distortions
anyway if we look at charts then
yesterday I made a point that these price behaviours
repeat quite consistently yeah
so price runs out
here's price is quite stable, it pops out
runs super, super inefficient, the volume
dries off, leaving behind
that void of buy liquidity, at least
so it did it twice here.
You had, so buy liquidity
there, sell liquidity there, a tiny
bit of weakness on the sell liquidity times
buy a volume shot, price runs out,
sets off the price chaser mechanism,
sell liquidity is running away, buy liquidity,
buy volumes chasing, chasing, chasing,
buy volume dries off, leaves
behind that thinly traded
area so imagine just a vacuum
and any old selling is able
to push price right back in.
In this instance
the buy liquidity would have accepted higher prices
is there. It's impossible for price to upheld
there without there being bi-liquity.
Yeah, otherwise it would have drawn straight back in
wouldn't it? Any selling that came
continued to come in with a push price down. Anyway, so
price builds up again. As you can see
the market order buying is not pushing price straight away.
It's actually kind of not there.
So the buy liquidity is they're holding price up, but the market orders, the volume, has dried off.
Variable volume, flow.
The volume, the flow of it, the flow rises, the flow contracts, the flow rises, the flow contracts.
The volume isn't constant.
It's not maintaining the same level of flow at each minute or each second.
The volume rises, volume contracts.
Volume rises, volume contracts.
Volume rises, sell equity disappears.
Price expands trying to find equity, creating that thinly traded move.
Volume dries off, leaving behind that weakness, and price subsequently draws right back in.
This is natural.
This is based off the structure of the market.
the price behaviors I'm talking about here
the large inefficient extension
the exhaustion and extension fill
that's the specific name of that behavior
is a function
it's a price behavior
that is created because of the market
at least the market organization
at least the way the market is set up
it's impossible for it to not happen
so now we have this behavior
which is going to consistently repeat over time
now you have to validate it don't just take my word for it
you can go out at any price chart
at any time in the year, at any
time in history, you'll
see these price behaviours repeat. More frequently
now, past 2008,
more frequently now, more consistently now.
But this still was
those areas of dimly traded
prices and price
drawing back into range, back in
back as far back as 1980s.
Oh yeah, you can clearly see it. See it there
at 8? Yeah, yeah, yeah,
where you just were.
So that's a
like a over
overemphasized
or over exaggerated type of example
what about the one to the right
here as well
yeah these are over-emphasized
over-exaggerated examples that we would
likely want to be in these trades
but the same thing's happening on a
minute scale here as well when you zoom in
price is stable price pops out
becomes super super inefficient
the sell liquidity is not here
not here not here not here it ends up
turning up here.
Simultaneously
to the market order
buy that
drew that push
price out
but the real
buy liquidity
the buy limit
orders
remain down here
so once
the buying dried off
there wasn't
significant
by liquidity
to hold price
up
any old light
selling was able
to push price
right back down
are you following me
yeah
now the same
thing repeats here
so price is stable
hardly anybody
being transacted
there will be
a momentary area
of buy liquidity
weakness
times
by a surge of cell volume, a very
light amount of cell volume, and
that triggers the response. Price
runs out. Chasing the
bi-liquity, it's not there, not there,
stretching that price run out
until it finally dries off and
hits an area of buyers.
Now, let me make a
point to you here. The point I'm ready
making is the reason price comes back
up is not necessarily
because of bias strength.
If there were strong buyers here, why did it not continue?
It was just a weakness on the other side.
Exactly. It's the weakness on the other side. So I'll illustrate an example. Here, there, there, and there, and there, and there at each of these levels. Two, four, six, eight, ten. If I, if somebody went nine million long, well, they get filled here, seven left over, five left over, three left over, one leftover, and finally the last level absorbs that one million, right? So now there's one million left over sell equity.
amount of sell liquidity at each price level change no then how is it then the last area of
sell liquidity stopped the buyers yeah yeah that's true right now we still know just because the
buying has stopped the market or the buying has stopped doesn't mean price is going to drop
now sellers have to come in or any volume has to come in the market and it will very very likely
draw price right back down yeah push price right back down but i i think the point
You know, I think it should be clear that the point I'm trying to make is the sell liquidity never changed.
But the further this $9 million went, fill, fill, fill, the weak of the $9 million got, left behind that weakness.
Hard any buy liquidity went up with a $9 million, creating that condition of thin buyers, not necessarily strong sellers, and still price went down on exhaustion.
Because it goes right back down to the real equity.
now typically that it's not always that you know so typically there will be a nice area of sell liquidity as well so rather than they being two million here usually there will be a nice area for example 101 million but the point I'm trying to illustrate here is you don't need strength here to push price down price goes to the less liquid side the less liquid side is created because of the way that volume is dealt off into the market as we've discussed yeah that makes sense so
this volatility is tradable you know price uh price pops out becomes super super inefficient the market order
buy and dries off doesn't necessarily hit strong sellers there but the sellers absorb the buyers there
and then whatever void was left behind any light selling pushes price down the same happens here
price is quite stable shoots out buying dries off hit some sell liquidity in the middle left
behind a weekly traded area weak by liquidity weakness in by liquidity
Any light volume pushes price right back down.
And as you can see, once it reaches back at the core price stabilizes.
If there was no bi-liquity at this origin, then sellers would have continued to push through.
Why?
If there was no bi-liquity here, there was nothing in the way to stop the next sell order to reach to the next level, no?
Yeah, it'd have to go down lower to find the next...
To wherever they're set by exactly.
So prices, from that you can retract.
retract a principle price simply finds liquidity if price is moving it's looking for liquidity
that ties directly in with price goes at less liquid side yeah looking for liquidity not trying to
take you out your position yeah and in this instance liquidity is on stop losses
liquidity is fucking limit orders yeah um but again price reaches this area of of bi liquidity
whatever by liquidity is left there sell orders dry off the volume dries off there's some cell
equity above price, there's some buy liquidity beneath price, subsequently we have a sell volume
shot at the right time, combined with a bit of weakness on the bids, and price goes smack
down to the next level. They literally would go whack. Find some buy liquidity. We're at this price
level here. The sell orders dry off. The market order selling dries off. Variable, so volume
shot, volume dries off within a matter of minutes. Variable volume flow.
variable meaning is changing up and down
volume meaning market orders
flow the flow of market orders
it's a critical
critical idea to connect with
because what that means is
in any long term price move
it's not going to be composed of buying buying
buying every second of every day all the time
actually you'll have
the real buy liquidity holding the trend up
volume shot on the buy side
pushes price out
because if there's strong buy liquidity
is likely thin sell liquidity
volume shock causes price
to go to less liquid side
the volume dries off
leaving behind that weakness
and price has to come back down
to find the buyers
maybe the buyer's turned up here this time
and the same thing repeats
so even in a trend
I can be short
wrong about the direction
right about my trades
time and time again
and as we've discussed
trading at the thinnest point of liquidity
where you have the biggest skewed part of the book
where there's the thinnest point of buyers
highest probability
the highest probability
and I keep using obviously examples of shorting
the same applies for down moves as well
buying
yeah it's like you love
you love selling
yeah I don't know I should have a look at my stats
but the reason I'd probably like selling right now
is cable's recently been trend at night
but that doesn't necessarily mean
You can't be a buyer within these environments.
You can or look at how you can.
Because if you have a high level of certainty that bi liquidity is turning off at these last areas
and that this moved down is simply trying to find the core inventory of bi liquidity,
then you can trade with the inventory of buyers as well.
You can be that with the flow trader.
You'll make more money this way in mobile type environments.
So if you know what Wi-Fi is that crypto that went to,
40k?
No.
So basically
there's one
cryptocurrency that went to
40k, double the price
of Bitcoin's
all time high.
When there is
bubble type environments,
so event-driven
states and price
continues to go higher
and high
and buyers continues
to accept
higher prices almost
forever,
then trading
with the strength
of the market
is a good show.
You'll make
for fucking shit
to the money.
Actually, that
reminds me.
Do you remember
when you put up
that picture of
ripple
yeah
I think
when I caught the low
yeah
you caught the low
and it went
exactly to
where you wanted
to do that
was crazy
yeah to your arrow
that was nuts
you get lucky
no you create your own
look
the way I think about
you you can expose
yourself to look
if you can identify
something
that has an 80 20 chance
of working out
if you want to
expose yourself
to that 80% chance
as many times as possible.
So, you know, you want to do it time and time again
as frequently as possible to expose yourself
to 80% chance of winning, turning up.
That doesn't mean you won't lose.
Actually, if there was an 80% 20% chance of winning,
if you applied that over a million times,
there's a certainty that you lose 20 times in a row.
Yeah, yeah.
You will lose 20 times in a row.
You just have to make sure that when you're losing,
there's no real downside.
so you can be there for the next runner
that's the difference
so if it was 80 to 20 chance
never bet your house
yeah right
because over a million times
you lose your house 20 times in a row
many many different times
but the only time really
I'd bet my house if it's like 99 to 1
then I'm happy to be homeless
the variance
the likelihood of having 20 losers in a row
is much much lower
do you have trades like that
where it's like 99 to 1
trading at the thinnest point
liquidity, it's guaranteed price is going to go your way. But you have the most skewed book here.
So the thinnest point of sell is there and thicker buy is there. Immediately as price moves away,
there's going to be some sell liquidity that turns up. So the probability of price going your way
straight away is only down there. Even one or two pips away from that, the probabilities are starting
to drop a tiny bit. That doesn't mean there still is not weakness here. But trading at the exhaustion,
point is almost certain, or it is absolutely certain that price will go your way, it's just
executing it and timing it and doing it consistently at that area is relatively difficult.
Yeah, okay.
You can build your skill and you know what, it's not impossible, but you have to have a lot of patience
and discipline, right?
You build that over time.
What you'll do is you'll make mistakes and you'll miss the exhaustion point, then you try to
buy it here away from the exhaustion point, and typically price will go your way.
sorry price will go against you now the problem with that is if i was long here i have that much
space to manage my trade yeah if you buy it late up here you have no space to manage your trade price
goes against you almost straight away so trading at the exhaustion point from a management of trades
it puts you in a better position even though it can be a few minutes different a few minutes a few
Pips difference and probabilistically price go in your way immediately the lack of the least amount
of drawdown the risk of the drawdown is the lowest at the exhaustion point so trading one of those
conditions is the most favourable and we're going to discuss like how to identify how to select the
levels as well but yeah you you hardly ever even in life have skewed probabilities like that
you drive a car a lorry could hit you a fucking bird could come through your window hit you in the eye
you take your eye out fucking uh two p coin could go it just doesn't matter you're walking
you're walking in central london bro if somebody could have dash the two p coin off i don't know
i was going to say afa tower i could lick you in london yeah it could lick you in your head
the chance of these things happening is is present but of course we know that god keeps us safe
now in life as well you're not exposed to the like typically you don't expose yourself to chance that
frequently right you might open a business every five years and it goes under every like yeah you're
not exposing yourself to chance that frequently where it has a significant effect on you whilst in
trading very very frequently you're vested in the outcome and you're exposing yourself to chance
even if it's 80 20 probabilities the possibility of 20 losers in a row is 100% over a big sample set
over a million examples.
So you have to realize that in trading
is almost certain that you're going to have periods
where the outcomes,
the outcomes of each chance are distributing
randomly and negatively.
They're not distributing favorably.
So you could do everything perfect
and still you're losing.
That is exactly what you're,
that's exactly what's going to happen in a game of chance.
This is down to probability.
but like I'm saying if you're trading under the exhaustion state price will go your way it
doesn't mean you'll make money though because price can go your way here and suddenly the
probability shift up there you know so you went long it was extremely favorable for
price to respond and then a few months later the probabilities have changed and now it's
unfavorable to be in that trade so you'd have to cut that trade or you or you take a loss
we of course look to identify the loser
and the change in probabilities within this period
I manage my trade super aggressively
and I avoid a huge amount of losses
but the point you're making here is
you cannot control the outcome of any individual
any individual circumstance
there's hardly a single circumstance
where you have skewed probabilities like this
so the point to take away from here is
even if it is relatively
high chance of you winning
you're still going to have
outcome series which are negative
negative outcome series
losing trades
happening sequentially in series
so loser loser loser loser loser loser
even though it has an 80 20% chance of winning
in that sense
you're exposed to randomness
but then I would argue if you're up in a business
you're exposed to randomness as well
and if you do
like I said if you drive a car
you're exposed to randomness
this isn't necessarily
gambling. You have
a methodology backed by
the structure of the market which
which has
is guaranteed for price to go in a certain
way over another
however that's only momentarily
I take it though
so say
you caught that low there
I take it that on the way down price
can show you some characteristics which
which could
tell you to get out of it
yes that's like I said
like I said I think a minute ago
we'll be able to identify the nature
of this the characteristics
it will present and represent
here will show weakness
on the buyers I'm going long
I need weakness in the sellers
right
if there's weakness in sellers and
strength on the bits
price should reflect that
we should see any move down
fail to beat the buyers
this is a low volume contraction
when the volume increases
it should quite easily
run through this thinly traded inefficient area back to the origin, right?
So throughout the series of each candle,
each second of these minute candles each,
price should never reflect the opposite, basically,
which is weak buyers, strong sellers.
We'll discuss the characteristics of winners and losers at due time,
but the point of making is if basically you're taking the idea,
you're taking the trade based on the idea that this thin sellers,
and thick, thick buyers here,
at the point of taking the trade,
it's almost impossible for price to go down if you're correct.
The response should prove to you that, you know,
so the response should prove to you that your idea is correct.
Now, you know, so, sorry, you don't know.
But if the response is showing you the state of liquidity,
can you not observe that response from trade entry,
from the first pip up to the second pip to the third pip linearly,
as it unfolds to determine if your idea was correct or not.
Yeah, you can.
So as prices unfolding, new information has coming out,
you can observe that information to determine
that if price is reflecting the state of liquidity,
your trade is trying to capture.
Yeah.
Your trade is trying to capture weak sell liquidity.
You're trying to trade to the less liquid side.
So when you take your entry,
the response should reflect as well,
less liquidity on the sell side.
Do you get it?
Yeah, yeah.
If at any point it starts to show
that there's weak buy liquidity,
the buy liquidity is too thin
the sellers are holding price down
then we again
we continuously observe an incoming information
and we can adjust
we can adjust our
basically we can respond to that new information
if the price the way it unfolds
reflects strong sellers
and fix our liquidity
again we can quickly adapt
now there is a unique
phenomenon I guess in trading
which is we know that distribution of outcome is random
probabilities are distributed randomly
you flip a coin
heads comes up you flip a coin doesn't mean
tails will come up yeah
it's not a linear distribution it's randomly
distributed but simultaneously
you have dynamic probabilities as well
so probabilities are always changing
there's like an infinite amount of variables that can combine
and affect
the state of liquidity so
for example
Boris Johnson
could have herpes and his mom could die
and that could result in him doing some mad shit
and that could affect the market.
Simultaneously, North Korea could launch a bomb.
Simultaneously, a million infinite amount of variables
could mix together and create some level of response from the market.
All of these things are changing all the time.
So the amount of variables that can combine and affect probabilities
is infinite, therefore probabilities are dynamic.
They're always changing.
One second, you can have a specific environment.
the next second they can completely change
price will always reflect that
so we can always observe price changes
as information about the state of liquidity
so that creates a demand for us to always track price
but the point I'm making here is
you have random distribution of outcome
distribution of outcomes random
and probably is a dynamic
these are two very very significant problems
you have to solve
first of all to kind of make trading halal
and secondly to even trade effectively
over time yeah and we'll come up with these solutions one of them is tracking price and incoming
information very closely and interpreting information in price to to assess that the probability is basically
all right similar to like a controlled experiment but we'll discuss that in due time it's like
the basis i'm setting out for you um you don't need to know the future you can simply observe price
now outside of all this all this chat your winners will develop in a certain way they'll
have specific characteristics notice here how price there was sell sell sell sell they got stretched
out it got thin thin thin thin thin yeah very thin and simultaneously would hit some buy liquidity
yeah the thinest point of sell liquidity thicker point of buy liquidity price immediately goes up
it comes into like a small pocket of sellers the buy the buy in the buying
the volume buying here dries off yeah right the volume contracts and a surge of sell volume
pushes price right back down because as you can imagine there was there's this thick out red let
there's buy liquidity here price run up on market order buying to this area of sell liquidity
the buy liquidity remain down there once the buy volume dried off any surge of sell volume at the
right time pushed price out to find the buyers back down there yeah yeah do you follow me yeah if those
if these buyers moved up price wouldn't have spiked down like that they actually remained back down at
the origin the court now the point to to make here is i if i go long price draws up sellers try to
push down again and if they were to travel through where the area of bi liquidity was that confirms to me
that there's no buyers there.
Even one pip beneath the area of bi-liquity
or one second for price spending beneath that area
where I expected it to be bi-liquidy,
that's information confirming to me
that there is actually no bi-liquidy there.
I can respond and cut the trade well ahead of my stop loss.
So the point I'm ready making here
is the price movement should reflect the state of liquidity.
And the idea here is there's more bi-liquity than the sell-liquity.
so price should go to a less liquid side
and that's exactly what we saw
there was significant bi-liquity holding price up
really very thin sell liquidity there
price contracted into low volume
so nothing was pushing price in any direction
but then when we got that surge and volume
then price ran out
so yeah hopefully that's some insight
into like how we can manage dynamic probabilities
and interpret
shifts and changes in probabilities
there might be it's very
very, very subtle information.
Like some people would see no difference
between price doing that or holding that initial low.
There is no real MS break here that people follow.
But we'll be assessing the whole price rundown
relative to like, yeah, basically we'll be assessing
the characteristics of the price run in its entirety
to determine its strength, the weakness,
what it's likely to do next based on previous price weeks.
but for now I'm kind of validating
that like you said
there's a large example of super
inefficiency here
that's event driven
but the same thing's happening on a minuscule
micro scale
which is classed as micro volatility
where you have air
of stability price shoots out
dries off draws back in
shoots out dries off drawers back in
all within this larger shoot
and kind of draw back in eventually anyway.
So the self-similarity prices
are repeating over and over and over again
because we know that price formation is
a result of market-to-limit order ratios.
That's it.
For price to have gone from here to here,
there would have been market order,
hardly any sell liquidity there,
sell limit orders there,
and price popped straight through to wherever there was sell limits.
That's the only reason for price formation,
market-to-limit order ratio.
From that, you can determine
which side of the market is,
thinner or weaker as obviously as price unfolds.
Yeah, so this is what we call microvolatility, which is basically normal order flow that's coming in from the wide variety of clients, generating price responses at the relevant liquidity providers.
So unintended volume shot from a small, small and medium size business, he goes long or they go long to manage some currency exposure into Japanese yen, the short.
that bitch that flow hits the bank's desk at the right time where there's a bit of weakness
triggers that price response yeah they follow me that price response causes these distortions
away from the the core area of liquidity so here's the core area of buy liquidity volume
short price distorts away from it it comes super super thinly traded once the volume dries
off again we know there's a vacuum left behind light volume price draws right back to
the level, back to the core liquidity,
back to a level of efficiency.
So the market's desire all times
is to facilitate trade.
Here, a lot of trade is being facilitated.
The market is perfectly efficient there.
Here, hardly any sellers are matching with buyers.
Even though there's a lot of sell volume,
there is no real trade being facilitated there.
The market isn't doing its job.
As a result of the behaviors of liquidity providers
like we discussed.
So we know, we know,
don't need to really care or give to you focus about where the market's going to go directionally,
it doesn't matter.
Wherever it goes, variable volume flow will occur, microvolatility of the back of order flow
will occur, and we can classify these two as liquidity dynamics.
The liquidity dynamics are a constant, regardless of market direction, my sentiment in the market,
doesn't really matter.
Order flow will generate these price responses.
It creates these conditions where there's weakness in one side.
we can take advantage of that
volatility. That's the point
and really, that's kind of the
crux of this approach.
The direction doesn't matter, but directionless
or bias, non-biased traders.
Just taking advantage of volatility.
You just want to get the weakness
on one side of the book.
That's it. If price runs out here, I don't give two fox.
The price runs up there, I don't give two fox.
Now, there is definitely a broad array of environments
if we start to become technical about it.
but simplistically, price can be in relatively efficient environments
or it can be in driven environments.
The reason I refuse to call these ranges
and I refuse to call that a trend,
a trend apply implies that price goes to a direction in a straight line,
but there's huge, huge volatility in today there.
This huge, huge amounts of volatility up and down
because the sellers dry off,
because that move down is moving away
from where the real sell liquidity is.
sell liquidity remains there
there's a bit of weakness on the buy liquidity
volume shot price runs all the way out
leaves behind that weakness
and then any buying that comes through
wants to buy liquidity you wants to sell liquidity
wants to sell orders are dried off
where is it where's price
going to go to find sell liquidity
yeah where is that where's price
oh yeah so there back to the origin
back to the last deal
yeah yeah
the last dealing range could be classified as inventory
which is what we'll call it
inventory as in a shop as an inventory in the back here
they keep a stock of something
so this price run on the way down
has a stock or inventory of sell liquidity moving along with it
every time price runs away from it
the move dries off price draws back to its inventory
it reloads on it and the next move ensues
it always draws back to the inventory
until imagine here the inventory can't hold anymore
buyers push through
the sellers will withdraw again
and prices likely to do that
it's obviously a possible scenario
but back to my point
the volatility is a function of the microstructure
of the market we trade the volatility
obviously there's more favorable types of volatility
than the other or than others sorry
there is more favorable types of environments
than others as well but only in each environment
we first need to come up with a somewhat of a visual framework to differentiate between them.
So like, how do I differentiate between two environments?
Well, we first need to be able to assess them, right?
That's why for now we're calling this inefficient, thinly traded,
and this is more stable where sellers and buyers are matched with volume quite efficiently, quite well.
Here, huge, huge sell volume, little buying happening.
Right. So that's already two categories that we can put price into when we're trying to assess market environment. Each of those categories will have different but and unique characteristics when we're observing prices within them. So it's laying out a playing field or it's laying out a solution in assessing market environment, which is always changing, which is always dynamic. So we can better identify which environment's which and what the characteristics of each of.
so if you're going to be a trade of that you know so let's let's tie this back into a general point
if market environment's always changing imagine price started to expand tomorrow
whoever sees that expanded that market environment has changed late he's a shit trader he had less
time to adapt to basically he he adapted to the change in market environment late
is very likely before he changed or fine-tuned his trading he was
trade in that new environment inappropriately.
Like I said, depending on the environment, inefficient, more efficient,
it has different characteristics.
That means there's different types of trades that work there.
You have to manage your trades different.
You have to select your trades differently.
Each of these environments have a different level of volatility.
Price responses have a different level of duration.
The characteristics are different here.
So we can see sell liquidity holds price down.
Here, you have two-way volatility,
bi-directional volatility.
So naturally, you can just expect
the environment has an effect
on the types of trades that work.
If then the trader sees an environment change too late,
he's been traded the market environment
completely wrong for the last,
ever since it changed.
That is the primary, primary reason.
You win sometimes, you lose sometimes.
In the periods you're winning,
it's not because you're a good trader,
it's because the market environment is conducive
for that side of trading.
When the market environment shifts,
typically people see it too late
and within that period of shift
and seeing it,
they've done their ass.
They lose their profit and more.
So not all of it,
but a large part of trading appropriately for markets
which are dynamic.
You never know what's going to happen next.
The market environment is always changing.
Probability is always changing.
These are three very big problems
that need solutions.
One of them is,
one of the problems
is market environment
the solution for that is
what we can attempt to solve it
first of all we need to be able to assess
the differences between the market environments
you get it like if you were building a program
for I don't know if you were code
in a program you need a fucking language
there in the first place to be able to build
that that desired program
in the first place within that language
each word or whatever is going to have
purpose built purposes
right
the same thing kind of applies for price environment
We need to be able to contextualize price quite accurately, differentiate between various states,
identify the characteristics of each state, so we can better assess what the most appropriate way to interact with it is.
That's what we'll be coming on to next.
But hopefully at this point we've discussed, we've gone over a few examples of how,
doesn't matter what time from it is, doesn't matter which period is.
What I say is, in effects at least, the price behaviors are a function of the microstructural.
which is the organizational rules
the transactional systems, the participant
behavior, all as a collective
result in very consistent price behaviors
from which we retract principle.
The principles so far are
market to limit order ratio is price formation.
Price goes to less liquid side
or prices always seek inequity.
Those are the two.
Basically it's the same thing.
And the other one was
it'll come back to me.
So market limit of order ratio, price goes to less liquid side.
fuck it
we'll definitely come back
you'll just say you want to
trade with a zed where the book is skewed
yeah so we want to trade under a condition
where the skewed liquidity
these principles
are oh the other one was variable volume
flow yeah these principles
are kind of explaining why
in a robust way he price does what it does
based off them we can also identify
trade opportunities like you just said
trading at the thinnest point in liquidity
why price goes to less the good side
why does the price run dry off
because the volume is variable
it's not constant it's not buy it's not
you know a hundred shot
it's going to get thinned out
it's not going to stay a hundred
so it's critical critical
that we come up with these kind of
that we see markets
through this prism of liquidity dynamics
which is factual
right there's no room for
speculation here
we're not saying that
a JP Morgan trader decided to go short
because his macro model
is saying that the pound is overvalued
nobody gives two folks about that
we don't apply the same models they're trading
we're not even trading the same venue as them
it's more to do with we're trading the nature of prices
which are a function of the market structure
so it's a critical
but yeah it's critical
to understand in my opinion to see markets
through this prism
because it brings a whole level of
necessary detail you see the market in a different
way she get it yeah yeah yeah but you know like here we had a really really thin move
price drew all the way back up then that move was relatively thin price true this is a much more
stable sell off on low selling not not aggressive selling but low volume selling price goes right
back to the core volume shop price goes right back up to the core notice the nature of these candles
they're not super aggressive and driven it's actually completely low volume here but still low volume
low buying and selling is completely sufficient
in pushing prices and less liquid side
because of the fact that there didn't sell
liquid either. There's nothing
there to stop the buying.
So imagine here
there was unlimited by limit orders.
Price would never go beneath that level.
Impossible. It doesn't matter
if the global central banks all came together and printed
off 100 trillion
on obviously a digital screen
and shorted it, prices never
go in any way because it's unlimited bids there.
You get it?
So if there is no, you know, the other principle, then you can retract from that is limit orders are friction.
Liquidity, aka limit orders, is friction.
If there's a lack of limit orders there, there's a lack of friction, any old light buying able to push price there.
And then, of course, over time, you'll come to find and will validate why this is a low volume state.
Just like price was really inefficient there.
It hits on by liquidity.
The selling dried off.
a left thin sell liquidity there
and any old buy volume was able
to push price right back up.
I'm sure we just saw it.
We can break that move down
into a bit more detail
as if we were zooming into it
with a fucking microscope.
Price sold off super super inefficient
or relatively inefficient
dried off as you can see
price goes nowhere.
If there was a huge amount
of buying and selling happening there
price would have moved
it would have gone to a less liquid side.
We already know there's less sell liquidity
and there's a little bit of sell liquidity
thinly distributed sell liquidity there
then why is it price stabilises
it has to be because there's no driving
volume for that short
period of time volume shot
thin sell liquidity triggers
the price response sell liquidity draws away the ask price
draws high the buy volume chases it
creating that thinly traded move that
rises quite rapidly and the buy
volume has subsequently dried off
we could take a shot deep printer
sellers there or it could fill that
inefficiency back down to call there but anyway
this price behavior is repeat on all scales
it doesn't matter what scale you look at it on
that was three ticks one of the smaller scales you can look at it on
we can look at it on the monthly scale as well
of course
of course for something to be inefficient
on the monthly
there had to be a long period of buying
consistently not constantly
but a long period of buying consistently
that's going to be your event-driven environment
do you get it
whereas the volume
the move on the three tick chart that we just saw
it doesn't mean there was a huge huge
buyer pushing price up there, it could have been a random volume shot from a small
algorithm that's been tasked with filling a large trade all day to day. It just came at the right
time. Are you following me? Yeah. So price filled that in efficiency, back down to core. It's stabilizing
for now. Another volume shot might push it out or another volume shot up might push it up. You
never know what's going to happen next. But what we did know that was thin.
here's that volume shot
so that movement out there
doesn't necessarily affect the big seller
doesn't reflect a big bank going short because you're long
nobody gives two fucks about that
it's just a random volume shot
creating the price response
that's called a micro volatility
compare that to macro volatility
which is event driven sentiment driven
driven long term selling
that has the same effect
of thinly traded which is relative
to the time frame dice
so it's not as thinly traded as a one-minute price run but this this move here is thinly traded compared to that area of monthly stability yeah right and for a price to sell off for such a long period there has to be an event it behaves slightly differently because it sells off for a longer period of time but the effect is the same it's still thinly traded compared to that once the sellers have dried off the middle was still thinly traded the middle was still thinly traded and the
origin was still the better area and that's exactly where price goes just the same way you have the
origin here price pumps out becomes massively inefficient in 2018 January there and comes all the way back
down to this core yeah just the same way we had the origin shot coronavirus event driven sell off
price draws right back up and after that high volume selling price stabilize into a low volume
state. After that high volume
buying, price is stabilised into low volume
state. High volume, low volume, low volume, high volume, low volume,
repeating price behaviours as a function
of the microstructure.
That's what we're looking at. That's what we're trading.
That's what we look at within the next, for the next
years to come.